<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.6.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-03-22T20:08:27+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Diogo Ferreira webpage</title><subtitle>Diogo Ferreira personal webpage.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">What the hell is a Bloom Filter?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/bloom-filter/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What the hell is a Bloom Filter?" /><published>2019-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/bloom-filter</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/bloom-filter/">&lt;p&gt;Hi there!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post I will describe what is a Bloom Filter, its purpose and scenarios where it can be useful to use one. I will also implement a Bloom Filter from scratch in Python, for an easier understanding of its internals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;goal-of-a-bloom-filter&quot;&gt;Goal of a Bloom Filter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Bloom Filter is a data structure with the goal of checking if an element is &lt;strong&gt;NOT&lt;/strong&gt; in a set in a fast way (for those who know Big O notation, the complexity of inserting and checking if an element belongs to a set using a Bloom Filter is O(1)). It can be very useful to prevent a computation-intensive task to be done often, simply by verifying if the element is &lt;em&gt;definitely not&lt;/em&gt; in a set. It is important to understand that the Bloom Filter is a probabilistic data structure: it can tell you that an element is not in the dataset with 100% probability, but it cannot tell you that an element is in the set with 100% probability (false positives are possible). Let’s talk about scenarios where a Bloom Filter can be used, and later on you will understand why the Bloom Filter has these characteristics, with a detailed explanation of its internals and an implementation in Python!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/img/bloom_filter.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/bloom_filter.png&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 80%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;figcaption style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;A bloom filter is usually used before a search in a set with slower access. The number of searches in the set can be reduced, so as the overall search time.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;scenarios&quot;&gt;Scenarios&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s think of some scenarios where such data structure can be useful to speed up the computation of some tasks. We can start by thinking in a router of a core network (those that you don’t have in your house :) ). It can be required for those routers to have an uplink speed of over 100 Gbit/s. The administrator can add a blacklist of IPs to block their access in the network. That means that everytime that the router receives a packet, at over 100 Gbit/s, it must look at his memory and perform, at best, a logarithmic search (O(log(n))) to check if the IP is blocked, knowing that most IPs are not blocked and that the search will not return any results for most packets. In this case, a Bloom Filter can be placed before the access to memory, to make sure that most packets do not need to wait the time of a search of an IP to be sent to the network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another scenario is the database example. When a database has millions of accesses per second, and most of the accesses are searches by a key that is not in the database, it can be important to reduce the impact of the calls on the database, for two reasons: if the number of searches is reduced, the database engine will reply faster to other accesses; if it is possible for a client to not wait for a search on the database and have the result (e.g. not in memory) without needing to access the database, the achieved speedup can be significant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, to speed up the search for a file in a folder with many files, the Bloom Filter can be used to check if the file is definitely not in the folder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More typical scenarios of usage of a Bloom Filter can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bloom_filter#Examples&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-a-bloom-filter&quot;&gt;What is a bloom filter?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s use the first scenario to exemplify the construction of a Bloom Filter. Imagine that you blacklist 100 IP’s. The easiest way to mark if an IP was blacklisted or not is to create a list with 100 bits, each bit is one IP. If an IP is blacklisted, we mark the position of the IP as ‘1’, otherwise is ‘0’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/img/empty_bloom_filter.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/empty_bloom_filter.png&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 30%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;figcaption style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;In this Bloom Filter, the IP number 4 is blacklisted and all other IP's are not.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-many-ips-there-are&quot;&gt;How many IP’s there are?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This implementation works… if only 100 IP’s are used. In reality, each IPv4 address has 32 bits, which means that there are 4 294 967 296 (2&lt;sup&gt;32&lt;/sup&gt;) possible addresses (some of them are reserved for private networks, broadcast, multicast and other special networks, but it is still a huge number)! And the number of blacklisted IPs will probably not exceed the hundreds, at maximum. We cannot afford to construct a list so large to use only a reduced number of entries. We have to find a mapping between an IP and an entry of a list. And that’s where hash functions come in!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hash-function&quot;&gt;Hash Function&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A hash function is a function that transforms an input of arbitrary length into a fixed-size value. In that way, we can create an array with fixed size and calculate the output of a hash function given an IP, and it will always generate a number smaller or equal to the size of the array. The hash function is not random, which means that for the same input, the output will always be the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/img/hash_function.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/hash_function.png&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 80%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;figcaption style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;A hash function receives an input that can be any string (in this case, an IP) and calculates a numerical representation. In this case, the numerical representation will be the position of the Bloom Filter corresponding to the input.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But wait… Something is not right. Let’s go back to our scenario. Imagine that we blacklist 100 IP’s. How does the hash function maps our 100 IP’s from a possible 2&lt;sup&gt;32&lt;/sup&gt; IP’s to 100 different values without storing any information from them? The truth is that it doesn’t. There will be collisions. The hash function guarantees that each IP will have a unique mapping to a number, but since there can be 4 294 967 296 (2&lt;sup&gt;32&lt;/sup&gt;) possible IP’s, it’s impossible to map them all to 100 different values. All the hash function can guarantee is that it scrambles the bits of the input such that the output follows a uniform distribution. This means that if you change the input of the hash function from 192.168.1.1 to 192.168.1.2, the output will probably be totally different, seemingly random (but not truly random, since each input will always map to the same output).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/img/collision.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/collision.png&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;figcaption style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Example of a collision. Two different IP's have the same hash, which means that their index in the Bloom Filter will be the same.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alright, now from the beginning: we blacklist 100 IP’s. Each IP will go through the hash function, and the result of the hash function will return a number smaller or equal to the size of the array. That number will be the index of the array that marks if the IP was blacklisted or not. But there will be collisions, so how do we handle that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s suppose that the IP’s 178.23.12.63 and 112.64.90.12 have the same hash. The first IP was blacklisted, the second was not. When we check if the hash of the second IP is in the Bloom Filter, it is, even though the IP was never blacklisted. Does this mean we have a bug?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember that in the beginning I said that the Bloom Filter has the goal of checking if an element is &lt;strong&gt;NOT&lt;/strong&gt; in a set. If the position of an element in the Bloom Filter is 0, that element is definitely &lt;strong&gt;NOT&lt;/strong&gt; in the set. However, if the position of an element in the Bloom Filter is 1, that element may be in the set, or it may be just a collision. All we can do is to reduce the probability of a collision, to reduce the number of times that the a memory access is needed to check if the IP is really blacklisted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;reducing-the-collision-probability&quot;&gt;Reducing the collision probability&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two main ways of reducing the probability of a collision, both at a cost. One possibility is to increase the size of the array. If we increase the size of the array (and consequently make the hash function return a number smaller or the same size as the new array size), the possibility of collisions decreases. Specifically, the probability of a false positive (the Bloom Filter return 1 when the element is not in the set) is (1-e&lt;sup&gt;(m/n)&lt;/sup&gt;), where m is the number of elements expected to insert in the filter and n is the size of the filter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other way to reduce the probability of a collision is to increase the number of hash functions. This means that in our scenario, for one IP, various hash functions will be used to encode that IP, and various locations in the array will be marked with 1. If we use k hash functions, the probability of a false positive is now (1-e&lt;sup&gt;(mk/n)&lt;/sup&gt;)&lt;sup&gt;k&lt;/sup&gt;, which means that the optimal number of hash functions is (n/m)*ln(2) (more details about the equations &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bloom_filter#Probability_of_false_positives&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/img/bloom_filter_two_hash_functions.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/bloom_filter_two_hash_functions.png&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;figcaption style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Example of a bloom filter with two hash functions. There is a collision in one of the hashes of the IP's, but it is possible to check that the IP 112.64.90.12 is not in the set, because one of its Bloom Filter positions is not 1.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s implement a Bloom Filter in Python in just around 50 lines of code and see the result!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next snippet of code, let’s start by creating a BloomFilter class. The constructor receives the size of the Bloom Filter and, optionally, the number of expected elements that the bloom filter will store. We will use the bitarray library to create an array of bits, and we set them all to zero. Finally, we set the number of hash functions to the equation that returns the optimal number of hash function, given the size of the bloom filter and the number of expected elements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;math&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;bitarray&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;bitarray&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;BloomFilter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;object&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;__init__&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;number_expected_elements&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;100000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;size&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;size&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;number_expected_elements&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;number_expected_elements&lt;/span&gt;

        &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;bloom_filter&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;bitarray&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;bloom_filter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;setall&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

        &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;number_hash_functions&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;round&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;((&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;size&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;number_expected_elements&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;math&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;log&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let’s define a hash function for the Bloom Filter. The implementation used (from &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/mengzhuo/180cd6be8ba9e2743753&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) implements the DJB2 algorithm. Let’s use it as a black box, since the explanation of the algorithm is beyond the scope of this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;_hash_djb2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;hash&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;5381&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ow&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;hash&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;((&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;hash&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;hash&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;ord&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;hash&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we have on hash function, but how do we create K hash functions? We can perform a simple trick that works. Instead of creating different hash functions, we will just append a number for each input in the hash function. The number will represent the hash function number that is being called. Because any small difference in the input of a hash function will result in a totally different hash, the result can be seen as a different hash function. Cool, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;_hash&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;item&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;K&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;_hash_djb2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;str&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;K&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;item&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let’s create a function to add an element to the Bloom Filter. For that, let’s iterate through all of the hash functions, calculate the hash for the item and finally put a 1 (or True) in the index of the hash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;add_to_filter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;item&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ow&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;range&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;number_hash_functions&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;bloom_filter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;_hash&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;item&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only thing that’s left is to create a function that checks if the element is &lt;em&gt;NOT&lt;/em&gt; in the Bloom Filter. For that, let’s iterate again through all the hash functions. If any of the Bloom Filter positions has 0, we can say that the element is definitely not in the set. Otherwise, if all positions have 1, we cannot say that the element is not in the set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;check_is_not_in_filter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;item&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ow&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;range&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;number_hash_functions&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;bloom_filter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;_hash&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;item&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;False&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s it! We have implemented our Bloom Filter. Let’s try it out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s create a simple test to check if it is working. Let’s create a Bloom Filter with 1 million entries, and then set the expected number of elements to 100 000. We are going to add the element “192.168.1.1” to our Bloom Filter as the blocked IP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;bloom_filter&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;BloomFilter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1000000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;100000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;base_ip&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;192.168.1.&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;bloom_filter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;add_to_filter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;base_ip&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;str&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To test it, we will iterate from 1 to 100 000, and check if the IP 192.168.1.i is in the Bloom Filter (there are no IP’s when i&amp;gt;254, e.g. 192.168.289, but in this case we are just performing a test). We will print the elements that we don’t know if they are in the set; all other elements that will not be printed are definitely not in the set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ow&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;range&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;100000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ow&quot;&gt;not&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;bloom_filter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;check_is_not_in_filter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;base_ip&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;str&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)):&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;base_ip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;str&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;192.168.1.1&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wow! Our Bloom Filter says that, from 100 000 IP’s, the only element that could be blocked is really our blocked IP! It did not produce any False Positive!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the full code of our Bloom Filter:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;math&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;bitarray&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;bitarray&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;BloomFilter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;object&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;__init__&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;number_expected_elements&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;100000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;size&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;size&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;number_expected_elements&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;number_expected_elements&lt;/span&gt;

        &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;bloom_filter&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;bitarray&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;bloom_filter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;setall&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

        &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;number_hash_functions&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;round&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;((&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;size&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;number_expected_elements&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;math&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;log&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;


    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;_hash_djb2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;hash&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;5381&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ow&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;hash&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;((&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;hash&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;hash&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;ord&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;hash&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;size&lt;/span&gt;


    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;_hash&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;item&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;K&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;_hash_djb2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;str&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;K&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;item&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;


    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;add_to_filter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;item&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ow&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;range&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;number_hash_functions&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;bloom_filter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;_hash&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;item&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;


    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;check_is_not_in_filter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;item&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ow&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;range&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;number_hash_functions&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;bloom_filter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;_hash&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;item&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;False&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;bloom_filter&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;BloomFilter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1000000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;100000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;base_ip&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;192.168.1.&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;bloom_filter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;add_to_filter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;base_ip&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;str&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ow&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;range&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;100000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ow&quot;&gt;not&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;bloom_filter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;check_is_not_in_filter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;base_ip&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;str&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)):&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;base_ip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;str&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s it for Bloom Filters! I hope that you have learned what a Bloom Filter is in detail and how to implement it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for sticking by!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="algorithms" /><category term="data structures" /><category term="big data" /><category term="bloom filter" /><summary type="html">Bloom Filter explanation</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Use agile in your dissertation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/use-agile-in-your-dissertation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Use agile in your dissertation" /><published>2019-10-06T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-10-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/use-agile-in-your-dissertation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/use-agile-in-your-dissertation/">&lt;p&gt;Hi there!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the previous dissertation posts, I noticed that the agile principles were the basis of some tips that I gave. There are remarking similarities between my tips and some agile principles. However, many people still fail in getting a good experience out of the dissertation because they don’t apply these principles. In this post, I will explain how the 12 Agile principles relate to the dissertation, and how to apply them to achieve a better dissertation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For all that don’t know what Agile is, here is a quick explanation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-agile&quot;&gt;What is agile?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Agile Manifesto was created in January of 2001 in a meeting in a Ski Resort, in Utah, by a restrict group of software development experts, such as Bob Martin (Uncle Bob), Kent Beck and Martin Fowler. The goal was to discuss lightweight practices for software development, to allow for better and faster software development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The agile manifesto is not a set of rules which you must strictly follow, neither a set of tools that you must use. Instead, it is a set of recommended principles that aim the collaborative development for a software project. It is based on iterative and incremental development methods, introduced many years before the Agile manifesto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s go through the 12 Agile principles and I will explain how I think that they can be applied - or not - in your dissertation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1---our-highest-priority-is-to-satisfy-the-customer-through-early-and-continuous-delivery-of-valuable-software&quot;&gt;1 - Our highest priority is to satisfy the customer through early and continuous delivery of valuable software.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This principle must be broken down into parts for better understanding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Our highest priority is to satisfy the customer” - Who is the customer in a dissertation?
The customer is always the entity that decides if the software is as good as requested. In a dissertation, the customer is the jury. Not only your supervisor, not the whole academia, and certainly not your dissertation presentation audience. Always have this in mind when writing the dissertation. The highest priority is to satisfy the jury to have a good grade.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“through early and continuous delivery” - How to approach early and continuous delivery?
Early and continuous delivery in a dissertation means to deliver work at a regular pace, following a defined plan with time-bounded activities. For a student, early and continuous delivery means not to leave all the work for the last week. This avoids unexpected difficulties that delay the work, by working through them and planning them with time. Besides, it avoids the regular last-week-sprint burnout. Most importantly, it gives your supervisor an idea of how your dissertation is going long before it ends and allows to change the requirements to improve your work.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“of valuable software” - What is valuable software?
In a dissertation there are two types of “valuable software”:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;the dissertation itself&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;additional work (software, data analysis, study, …)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both of them should be approached to satisfy the jury through early and continuous delivery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2---welcome-changing-requirements-even-late-in-development-agile-processes-harness-change-for-the-customers-competitive-advantage&quot;&gt;2 - Welcome changing requirements, even late in development. Agile processes harness change for the customer’s competitive advantage.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;width:100%;height:0;padding-bottom:42%;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://giphy.com/embed/2sfgo6v1ihOGKVptoB&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; style=&quot;position:absolute&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;giphy-embed&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://giphy.com/gifs/disney-trailer-toy-story-4-2sfgo6v1ihOGKVptoB&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a dissertation, this is a very important difference from enterprise projects. In enterprise projects, we should welcome changing requirements because the client pays for the software, and the software is designed for the client. However, most of the dissertations are individual work, and most of the requirements are defined by the student. Although the vision, scope and main goal can be defined by the supervisor, the main requirements are usually defined by the student; besides, a big advantage of the Agile processes does not happen for the dissertation. In an Agile environment, there are regular meetings between the development team and the client. In a dissertation, the client is the jury, so the meetings will be only with the supervisor. Besides, every time that the supervisor asks to change something, it can change your timings for the dissertation deliveries and presentation. So be careful with changes. If you change the requirements of your dissertation, go ahead and apply that to your work. However, if new requirements are added by the supervisor, think carefully if they make sense, and feel free to discuss with him/her his validity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With one month left for the delivery of the dissertation, however, I would advise you not to make major changes in requirements, because your delivery can be at risk. Before that, feel free to test and try new things, and add them to your work if they are useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3---deliver-working-software-frequently-from-a-couple-of-weeks-to-a-couple-of-months-with-a-preference-to-the-shorter-timescale&quot;&gt;3 - Deliver working software frequently, from a couple of weeks to a couple of months, with a preference to the shorter timescale.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This principle can be adapted from “working software” to “readable pieces of your dissertation”. Yes, the dissertation should be made incrementally, and although sometimes it can be hard to write consistent texts without having all the research and implementation done, leaving all the writing to the end it is usually not a good choice, because when writing you will think about new possibilities that can enhance or change your work. You can even detect flaws that you left unnoticed when implementing your work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of that, you should write everything that you do. Even if later on that part can be deleted because it is out of scope, or it is not used - it doesn’t matter. If you are working for your dissertation, everything that you do is important and needs to be in the document. With that, you will deliver “readable pieces of your dissertation” incrementally, and later on it will be much easier to rewrite (if needed) and organize your dissertation’ chapters based on the text that you already have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what is frequent? What should be the time interval to deliver work? Just like in Agile, it depends on your work, of yourself and your supervisor. However, I would argue that a meeting once a week with your supervisor to show him/her what you have done is a good time interval. It gives you time to show the work that you did that week and to discuss what to do in the next one. Two-week meetings are also a reasonable choice, but more than two weeks is too much. You can get lost, do something that is not in the scope of your work, or just don’t know what to do, and it will only be discussed in the next meeting. Prefer short weekly meetings to long monthly meetings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4---business-people-and-developers-must-work-together-daily-throughout-the-project&quot;&gt;4 - Business people and developers must work together daily throughout the project.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;width:100%;height:0;padding-bottom:100%;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://giphy.com/embed/l0IyokIkZEXvWnXGw&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; style=&quot;position:absolute&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;giphy-embed&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://giphy.com/gifs/netflix-bill-nye-the-science-guy-l0IyokIkZEXvWnXGw&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This principle is simple and logical: you and your supervisor must work together. Working together does not mean that your supervisor should start doing your dissertation - it just means that each one must do his job to reach the desired output. You must do your work and your supervisor must supervise you, advise you, guide you, help you when you need, give you the tools you need and stop you when you do anything wrong - not just give you the requirements and wait for what you will do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I need to emphasize “throughout the project”. Just like in the last principles, “throughout” implies a consistent work discussed in regular meetings over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5---build-projects-around-motivated-individuals-give-them-the-environment-and-support-they-need-and-trust-them-to-get-the-job-done&quot;&gt;5 - Build projects around motivated individuals. Give them the environment and support they need, and trust them to get the job done.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am going to split this principle into two sub-principles. Firstly, to build projects around motivated individuals is to assure that you and your supervisor have the motivation needed to do your work. Many things will go wrong - they always do - and what separates a great from a median work is your willingness to tackle the problems and to work around them. It is not expected for your work to follow a straight path, and you should explain your difficulties in the dissertation, as well as how you tackled them to achieve your goal. An unmotivated student will just avoid the difficulties and find an easy way out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latter part of the principle is about trust and support. Make sure your supervisor trusts you. Be totally honest with him/her, explain regularly your difficulties and don’t be shy to ask anything you need. Do you need a specific GPU, a virtual machine, or anything else, just ask him/her. He/she is there to help you with anything you need that is out of your control. Don’t be afraid of saying that you spent a week and you didn’t understand a topic or a paper. Trust him/her to help you do your dissertation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;6---the-most-efficient-and-effective-method-of-conveying-information-to-and-within-a-development-team-is-face-to-face-conversation&quot;&gt;6 - The most efficient and effective method of conveying information to and within a development team is face-to-face conversation.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;width:100%;height:0;padding-bottom:56%;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://giphy.com/embed/xThuW4sMMCqvaczToI&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; style=&quot;position:absolute&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;giphy-embed&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://giphy.com/gifs/the-grinder-fox-face-tv-xThuW4sMMCqvaczToI&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regular face-to-face meetings are the most efficient way to adjust your work with your supervisor’s expectations. Sure, e-mails and chat messages do come in handy for quick and small questions that you may have and you need the answer ASAP, but nothing beats a face-to-face conversation. Video-conferencing is another way to hold meetings, but it should not be a common way. It should only be applied when one of the intervenients is temporarily away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;7---working-software-is-the-primary-measure-of-progress&quot;&gt;7 - Working software is the primary measure of progress.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said above in 3, “working software” in this case can be adapted to “readable pieces of your dissertation”. Yes, there are other ways to measure your progress, mainly based on your work, and they vary on a case-to-case basis. However, what will be evaluated is your dissertation, so the dissertation is the ultimate measure of progress. Start writing as soon as you start doing some work, even if the work is still not finished. Because if have a lot of work but you do not write about it, your work will not be taken into account and you will end up with a poor dissertation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;8---agile-processes-promote-sustainable-development-the-sponsors-developers-and-users-should-be-able-to-maintain-a-constant-pace-indefinitely&quot;&gt;8 - Agile processes promote sustainable development. The sponsors, developers, and users should be able to maintain a constant pace indefinitely.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This principle is very important for a dissertation if you want to reach the end of your work without feeling burnout. It is very important to keep a constant pace of work. It is Ok to work more than 8 hours a day once a week, but not more than that. It is important to separate your work from your personal life for you to feel accomplished and for not getting obsessed with minor obstacles that may seem like the end of the world. Impose on yourself a 40-hour week schedule for work and follow it. If you don’t do it, you may end up working tirelessly for your dissertation but with very low productivity. It will harm not only yourself but also your dissertation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;9---continuous-attention-to-technical-excellence-and-good-design-enhances-agility&quot;&gt;9 - Continuous attention to technical excellence and good design enhances agility.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is something you should do not only in your dissertation but also in your future career. If you plan carefully your work and if you work with pride, it will reflect on your dissertation and presentation. Even if you do not notice, experient people in every area acknowledge and know how to differentiate between work done with pride and work just to pass the subject. Technical excellence differentiates the median from the great workers in every area - and that can be the difference between an 18 and a 20 in the dissertation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;10---simplicitythe-art-of-maximizing-the-amount-of-work-not-doneis-essential&quot;&gt;10 - Simplicity–the art of maximizing the amount of work not done–is essential.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love this principle. Because everyone mistakes “work with pride” with “you must do everything that you have planned for your dissertation”. That’s why you plan things: to prioritize what is important and to do things in importance order. If a specific feature will take two weeks to be done and it will not make much of a difference in your dissertation, then why doing it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pareto Principle, also known as the 80/20 rule, says that approximately 80% of the effects come from 20% of the causes. If you pay attention to your life, this principle applies to many things. In your dissertation, 80% of what you will write will be based on 20% of the work. Besides, 80% of your grade will be based on only 20% of your dissertation. Pay attention to that and focus on what’s important - identify your 80% and make them shine. If you have free time, work on parts of the other 20%, but don’t waste much time with them - they are not that important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;11---the-best-architectures-requirements-and-designs-emerge-from-self-organizing-teams&quot;&gt;11 - The best architectures, requirements, and designs emerge from self-organizing teams.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dissertation is a one-person work (two with the supervisor), so it may look that this principle does not apply to the dissertation. However, you have to look at yourself as “your team”. Because the work is yours more than anybody else, you will have the last word on deciding the architectures, requirements and designs, so do it wisely. Do not accept architectures that are imposed by anyone if you do not agree with them, because you are the one who will have to answer for them sooner or later. Don’t be afraid of creating your own architectures or requirements if they make sense to you. Self-proposed implementations are much valuable in a dissertation and show that the student has deep knowledge about the topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;12---at-regular-intervals-the-team-reflects-on-how-to-become-more-effective-then-tunes-and-adjusts-its-behavior-accordingly&quot;&gt;12 - At regular intervals, the team reflects on how to become more effective, then tunes and adjusts its behavior accordingly.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;width:100%;height:0;padding-bottom:43%;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://giphy.com/embed/DfSXiR60W9MVq&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; style=&quot;position:absolute&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;giphy-embed&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://giphy.com/gifs/alan-DfSXiR60W9MVq&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should use this principle with yourself. Sometimes we work so fast and have so many things to do that we forget of reflecting on what we did well and what we need to improve. Once a week take 10 minutes to think about what you have done in that week, what was correctly done and what can be improved. After a month of retrospectives, you will find it very useful to improve your work habits and you will be amazed when checking your performance improvement simply by thinking on what you did wrong and taking preventive measure to not happen again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it, thanks for sticking by until the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See ya on other posts!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="thesis" /><category term="dissertation" /><category term="agile" /><summary type="html">Take advantage of the 12 Agile principles for a better dissertation</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to have an A+ dissertation/thesis (IV/IV)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/how-to-have-a-thesis-part-4/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to have an A+ dissertation/thesis (IV/IV)" /><published>2019-09-13T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-09-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/how-to-have-a-thesis-part-4</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/how-to-have-a-thesis-part-4/">&lt;p&gt;Hi there, and welcome to the last part of this series!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you didn’t read the previous post, check it out &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-have-a-thesis-part-3/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I am summarizing tips I would give myself before starting the dissertation, explaining my good and bad decisions along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before, a heads up: the content of this blog post is highly subjective and related to my dissertation experience, so don’t take it as the ground truth. But do think critically about my advice and, whether you agree with them or not, comment on what you think about it&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is divided into four parts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-have-a-thesis-part-1/&quot;&gt;I - 3 tips for before starting the writing of the dissertation;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-have-a-thesis-part-2/&quot;&gt;II - 4 tips for during the writing of the dissertation;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-have-a-thesis-part-3/&quot;&gt;III - more 4 tips for during the writing of the dissertation;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IV - 3 tips for after the writing of the dissertation.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post, I will give pieces of advice on what to do after the writing of the dissertation is done. Let’s start!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;after-the-dissertation&quot;&gt;After the dissertation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;12---review-it-more-than-once&quot;&gt;12 - Review it more than once!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have &lt;strong&gt;FINALLY&lt;/strong&gt; written your dissertation. It’s finally over! But… is it? Every time you read a paragraph of your dissertation you change something. And now you receive the reviewed version of your supervisor, full of changes, and you have to rewrite everything. How many times do you need to review it until it’s done?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-experience&quot;&gt;My Experience&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the dissertation was written, I reviewed it once before sending it to my supervisor. In that review, besides syntax changes, the major changes done were to the introductions and conclusions of each chapter, that were changed to reflect the chapters’ content. It was also done many changes in the text to make it more clear and objective. After that, I send it to my supervisor. I got a little worried because the final reviewed version was only delivered to me days before the final date to send the final version, but I had the luck of my supervisor making all the minor changes in the document itself. So, when it was delivered to me, I only needed to perform a quick second revision and to make one or two major changes, mainly in the organization of the chapters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-advice&quot;&gt;My Advice&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After having everything written, I think you should review it at least two times. The first time is a coherency check. Check if the paragraphs and the chapters are coherent between each other. Check if the references are correct. Check if your introduction chapter mentions correctly all chapters and that it provides an overview of your entire work. Check if the introductions and conclusions of each chapter are coherent with what is in each chapter. And more importantly, check if what you write is what you mean, and make an effort to understand if another person would understand what you have written. After the first review is done, you can send it to your supervisor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your supervisor will send you a revised dissertation/thesis (hopefully). Now you’re ready for the second review. In the second review, you will mainly apply the changes that your supervisor advised you to (if you want, obviously; do not forget that it is your work, you have the last word!), and you will perform the grammar and syntax check. I advise you to use Grammarly: it gives you good tips on how to improve your writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, leave at least three weeks for this process. One week for your first review, one week for your supervisors’ review and one week for your second review. Further revisions can be made, but you will probably only perform minor changes, and it is not needed to review the whole document since you have already done it two times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;13---save-one-week-for-presentation-training&quot;&gt;13 - Save one week for presentation training&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;width:100%;height:0;padding-bottom:69%;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://giphy.com/embed/3o7qDEq2bMbcbPRQ2c&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; style=&quot;position:absolute&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;giphy-embed&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://giphy.com/gifs/mic-drop-peace-out-obama-3o7qDEq2bMbcbPRQ2c&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s face it: your grade will be set because of your dissertation, not because of your presentation. At most, the presentation will be used to decide between two grades, if the jury is uncertain. However, because it is a public presentation, we all get nervous and anxious before it happens. How much should we focus on presentation training? What should we do to prepare ourselves for that moment?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-experience-1&quot;&gt;My Experience&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before the presentation, I was scared of this moment. What if the jury did not like my work? What if they discovered that the work that I have done was simple, and everyone could do it, and what I had done was of no use? To avoid that, I trained hard for the presentation the week before. I made the first version of the presentation and I asked a lot of people for opinions and improvements. Then, I started focusing on what I was going to say. I trained for more than 20 times. For every training, I would adjust just a little bit the presentation - for me to remember what I was going to say; to explain information in graphical form and more explicitly; to be easier for non-experts to understand, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I knew possible flaws, omissions or questions about my work, I wrote them and I also wrote the answer that I would give if they were answered to me. That gave me more confidence about my work because I knew that I was probably not going to be surprised with questions that I did not know how to answer (spoiler: none of the questions that were asked was on the list; all the questions were easier to answer).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the day of the presentation, I knew everything that I was going to say. Curiously, I was not nervous. I was very confident that my presentation was going to good. And looking back, it went so much better than what I have always expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-advice-1&quot;&gt;My Advice&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leave one week for presentation training. Use the first day for creating the presentation. Then, the technique is the same as the writing of the dissertation/thesis: iterate. Present to your supervisors, friends, family, colleagues, … And train, train, train. Ask them to take notes of things they thought are wrong, things that they do not understand or just things that they do not like. If you make 3 presentations per day on the other days of the week, and you make the changes that were told you to by your audience, you will find yourself with a better presentation and with more confidence in your presentation. In this phase, training is really important for you to memorize what you will say, and to create mechanisms to present better - you will do that almost automatically with more training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, you will notice that the training is of no use anymore: you always say the same things, take more or less the same time and there not many critiques to improve your presentation. That’s when you know you are ready to present with confidence, with no anxiety whatsoever. You have rehearsed so many times that you just need to present one more and say the same things you did in the presentations before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want, you can write down the questions that you are expecting to hear from the jury. In my case, none of them was asked, but it gave me more confidence in the presentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;14---you-are-the-master-of-your-own-work&quot;&gt;14 - You are the master of your own work!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I have written 11 books but each time I think ‘Uh-oh, they’re going to find out now. I’ve run a game on everybody, and they’re going to find me out.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;—Maya Angelou&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Impostor syndrome. Do you know what it is? It’s that feeling you get when you think that you are not worthy of what you achieved - someone was wrong in choosing you, you are clearly not good enough, and all your success was just a lucky sequence of events. Don’t worry: 70% of people feel this way, according to a study in the International Journal of Behavioral Science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In that study, it is said that those with imposter syndrome tend to be perfectionists and to spend more time in their work just to make things perfect. Congratulations: if you have the imposter syndrome, you’re probably doing a good job. But it can be hard to deal with imposter syndrome in long-term projects. The motivation starts to decrease and you start questioning yourself and your work. If you’re not confident in your work in the presentation, the jury will notice and it will start to make more technical questions and it will doubt your answers. How do you become confident in your work?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-experience-2&quot;&gt;My Experience&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thankfully, my supervisor has always reminded me of how good my dissertation was. Because she knew me well, she knew that I would not relax if she said that, it would only give me more motivation to keep working. When I was not motivated (it happened 3 or 4 times), I called a meeting with her and I would explain to her why that was happening. The work was re-scheduled and adapted until I was comfortable and motivated for what I had to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-advice-2&quot;&gt;My Advice&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like I said in the previous tip, it gives you more confidence to take notes of the downsides of your work, to think about adequate responses if it comes up in the presentation. Even if they do not come up, it gives you more confidence in your work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No one in the world knows more about your work than yourself. You have been working at least for a year in your dissertation/thesis: no one knows more about the cahracteristics, the difficulties, the pros and the cons of your work. Remember: your goal is not to make the perfect dissertation/thesis. In fact, no dissertation is perfect: there are great dissertations that completely fail their main objective. The most important are the conclusions: if you did all over again, would you change anything? Say it in the conclusions and in the future work. Remember what Einstein said,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Failure is success in progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you totally fail, say why to help someone not to fail. Or to fail better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Explain what you have failed in your presentation. Be clear and don’t come with excuses. The jury knows when the students are honest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;15---write-a-paper&quot;&gt;15 - Write a paper!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;width:100%;height:0;padding-bottom:56%;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://giphy.com/embed/XIqCQx02E1U9W&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; style=&quot;position:absolute&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;giphy-embed&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://giphy.com/gifs/XIqCQx02E1U9W&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are at the end of this dissertation (or you have already presented your work) and your supervisor wants you to write a paper (or more) about it. He/she says that your contribution with your dissertation/thesis can help others in the field - and it can also help you to have a higher grade. You get excited, but at the same time writing a paper also means more work. If you are finishing your masters, you probably have never written a paper, and you don’t know where to start. What should you do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-experience-3&quot;&gt;My Experience&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Months before the dissertation presentation, I submitted a paper to an international conference. The result came back in the day before the dissertation presentation: it was rejected. My supervisors came to me saying that it just needed a few tweaks to be accepted in another conference, that I had nothing to worry about. I relaxed and, as I said before, the dissertation presentation went really well. After the dissertation presentation, besides the rejected article being reviewed to be submitted, I made another conference paper and a journal paper, about different topics approached in the dissertation. I still don’t know if any of them will be accepted, but I know that with the rejection of the first paper, I learned a lot about writing papers and the probability of the other papers being accepted is much higher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-advice-3&quot;&gt;My Advice&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are in doubt about writing a paper, my advice is to go for it. Share your work with others. By my experience, students regularly underestimate the potential of their projects: try to submit a paper and then wait for the feedback. If the feedback is negative (the paper was rejected), don’t worry. Rejections happen. Use it to improve your work with world-class specialists in your topic, even if some reviews seem totally wrong. If that happens, maybe it’s because the supervisors did not understand your work, and you should explain it better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing a paper is different from the work you have done up to this point. You have to use your summarization capabilities for the reader to be able to understand what you did in your work. Writing your first paper can be confusing, due to lack of practice, and very boring, due to the number of hours you will be reviewing it and changing it, with the feedback from your supervisors. Just as in the dissertation/thesis, you have to discuss critically the consequences of your work. Even the cons of your work should be discussed. But do not fear: when the paper is accepted, you know that it was all worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it for our series!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for sticking by until the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See ya on other posts!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="thesis" /><category term="dissertation" /><category term="tips" /><summary type="html">15 tips for your thesis/dissertation - 4/4</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to have an A+ dissertation/thesis (III/IV)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/how-to-have-a-thesis-part-3/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to have an A+ dissertation/thesis (III/IV)" /><published>2019-09-06T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-09-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/how-to-have-a-thesis-part-3</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/how-to-have-a-thesis-part-3/">&lt;p&gt;Hi there!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you didn’t read the previous post, check it out &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-have-a-thesis-part-2/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I am summarizing tips I would give myself before starting the dissertation, explaining my good and bad decisions along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before, a heads up: the content of this blog post is highly subjective and related to my dissertation experience, so don’t take it as the ground truth. But do think critically about my advice and, whether you agree with them or not, comment on what you think about it&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is divided into four parts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-have-a-thesis-part-1/&quot;&gt;I - 3 tips for before starting the writing of the dissertation;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-have-a-thesis-part-2/&quot;&gt;II - 4 tips for during the writing of the dissertation;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;III - more 4 tips for during the writing of the dissertation;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-have-a-thesis-part-4/&quot;&gt;IV - 3 tips for after the writing of the dissertation.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;8---the-dissertation-is-a-marathon-not-a-sprint&quot;&gt;8 - The dissertation is a marathon, not a sprint!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;width:100%;height:0;padding-bottom:100%;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://giphy.com/embed/sRKg9r2YWeCTG5JTTo&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; style=&quot;position:absolute&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;giphy-embed&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://giphy.com/gifs/running-run-runs-sRKg9r2YWeCTG5JTTo&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This advice is not about your dissertation work, or about your writing. Is just about you. And your time. In a dissertation work, everyone has moments when they thought everything is lost. That there is nothing valuable in your work. That it is so frustrating that you can’t wait for it to be finished. This piece of advice is not about how to deal with those times (sorry, I am not a motivational speaker). It is about how to avoid them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-experience&quot;&gt;My Experience&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tend to get overanxious about the work that I need to do. I tend to work a lot in the beginning. And that’s what I did. So much that before the half of the schedule of my work, I had already written the equivalent of a “regular” dissertation. After I understood that I didn’t need to overwork to finish my dissertation (if I wanted, it was already done), I rarely spent after hours working on my dissertation as I did previously. I played a &lt;strong&gt;LOT&lt;/strong&gt; of Football Manager. I played the guitar. I spent more time in Scouts. I saw many Youtube videos about random and uninteresting things. Curiously, I did not stop being productive. I did as much work as before, but with a lot more fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-advice&quot;&gt;My Advice&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Relax. I learned that it is important to shut down when you get out of the office and distract yourself with other things. It helps you avoid burnout and it is clinically proved that it improves your productivity the next day. Whether you want to play a game, or see a movie, or just do nothing (doing nothing is also important!), do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides, time is really important if you want to be productive. Create a schedule of what you propose yourself to do the next day, even if you don’t stick to it. Consider what are the next things to do and how long will take you to get them done. Everything will be easier if you keep a steady pace with your work. If you have done less than what you have scheduled for a day, do not overcompensate. All-nighters are clearly not worth it, and roadblocks are inevitable. Just adjust your schedule for the next day and try it again. If you do that, the dissertation work will be &lt;strong&gt;SO&lt;/strong&gt; much easier. Because the dissertation is a marathon, not a sprint, and you must be mentally ready for the long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;9---when-to-pivot-your-work&quot;&gt;9 - When to pivot your work?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not so uncommon to find supervisors that are constantly shifting the objective of the dissertation. There are several reasons for it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they saw a new paper with interesting results;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they do not understand in depth the area you are working in;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the results you have are useless;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you are not being productive/you are not motivated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When and why should you accept to pivot your work in the middle of a dissertation?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-experience-1&quot;&gt;My Experience&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did not completely pivot my work, but it has evolved over the year. In the beginning, the goal was to use machine learning to forecast network metrics. After that was done, we focused on some specific forecasting scenarios interesting for the network operator. After that, we thought that it was interesting to create a real-time distributed architecture to test the forecast - the focus of my work changed from machine learning to software engineering. In the end, two scenarios were tested with the forecasts implemented in the architecture to improve the network - again, the focus changed from software engineering to solving a real network problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Althought I did the work I had planned to do, I did much more than that. My dissertation was not only a machine learning problem: it had grown over time. It solved real scenarios in a 5G network with the help of machine learning and a dedicated architecture for forecasting. It is comprehensible and even natural that the dissertation work evolves over time. However, many of my friends reached mid-year with a totally different dissertation from what they were expecting. They became bored, unmotivated and unconfident about their work. They did not like what they were doing, because that’s not what they signed up for (or at least what they thought they signed for). What did they do differently from me? It was their fault? It was their supervisors’ fault?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-advice-1&quot;&gt;My Advice&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is hard to determine who’s fault it is without looking at it on a case-by-case basis. However, there is some advice I can give.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take a look at tip &lt;em&gt;Understand the basics before diving in!&lt;/em&gt; (part 1). This is the least you can do to not being caught up in the same situation that my friends were in. Talk with your supervisor and discuss what is the schedule for your work. Then, learn more about what you will do. That will help you to save some time and to have something done early. Having work done in an earlier phase is essential to discuss the scope of your work and validate our hypothesis. If you have to pivot, the earlier you do it the better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another essential trick is to have a personal schedule for the dissertation. Be realistic. It helps you to understand which foot you are in, and how many hours do you still need to put in to get the job done. It will also help you to list upfront all the problems you think you may find in your implementation. Do you need license X and your University does not have it? Do you need a computer with special requirements? The earlier you ask for it, the better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you really have to pivot your work, do it because of you. Do not pivot if your supervisor thinks that what you are doing is uninteresting and it will not produce any results. Yes, you should hear him and take his/her advice, but sometimes you really have to stand up for yourself. If you have done fruitful work, why give up? If you are on a later stage of the dissertation work, maybe pivoting will not produce any good results. You will take more time to understand and to redo everything you had done until then, and you will probably miss your personal deadlines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But when should you pivot then? For my experience, the main reason you should pivot is if you are not motivated and you have found a new problem that you want to solve and that you think you can do it. Obviously, this involves knowledge about the area you are pivoting. Otherwise, you may end up in the same situation as before. The interesting results are a secondary reason and they are closely related to your motivation. If you are motivated is because you think you think you can get interesting results, and vice-versa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;10---how-much-time-should-i-work-per-day&quot;&gt;10 - How much time should I work per day?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surely some students work more than 12 hours a day to get their dissertation done. Some students work around 4 hours a day and also get their dissertation done at the same time. How much time should you work per day?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-experience-2&quot;&gt;My Experience&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I began my dissertation work, I worked endlessly. Sometimes more than 12 hours every day. &lt;strong&gt;Every day&lt;/strong&gt;. Looking back, it was a bad decision. Some months after, I realized that I was only productive for around 6 hours of that 12, and I changed my working habits. I worked only on workdays, 8 hours a day, just as if I worked for a company. Surprisingly, I started being even more productive than before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-advice-2&quot;&gt;My Advice&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not a hard question. Around 8 hours at workdays. That’s it. It’s the mean number of hours that a “regular” worker works in a job. It is also proved to be effective. If we worked for more than that, we became unproductive, tired and unmotivated. Of course, there are exceptions. If you like to work 12 hours a day in three days of the week and rest the other four, you can do it if it suits you. However, it is not what has proven to be successful for most people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t feel pressured by the ones that say that you should work more than that - it is unrealistic to expect more and better work just because you work more hours. Mainly in a dissertation, where critical thinking is key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe sometimes you will feel that you are procrastinating your work, and all you ever want to do is to see Youtube videos or read a book. When that happens, try to enforce yourself a time management rule, such as the Pomodoro technique: 25 minutes of work followed by 5 minutes of a break. The rule is adjustable: if you are feeling productive, there is nothing wrong in duplicating the work and break time (50/10). After you do it for some time, it will become natural to you the work-&amp;gt;break cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, I almost forgot one thing. It is OK to take breaks. Actually, it is essential to take breaks. It helps you and your body to focus. A longer break in the morning and another in the evening (15 minutes) to eat a snack will help you boost your productivity. When you are writing, it is common to feel the writer’s block - the feeling that you don’t know what to write or where to start writing. Take a break. Go chat with someone. Get up and go for a walk. It will help you clear your mind. When you come back it will be easier to end up writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;11---the-first-goal-is-to-get-a-draft-not-to-get-it-written&quot;&gt;11 - The first goal is to get a draft, not to get it written&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/img/thesis-5.jpeg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/thesis-5.jpeg&quot; style=&quot;width:70%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;figcaption style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Don't worry if the first version is a mess. Rewrite it. It will be better the second time.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the last piece of advice during the dissertation. Many students are very concerned about their writing from the very first moment. So much concerned that for every line they write, they spend an hour looking at it and thinking about how they can improve it, to be no less than perfect. This is common to happen in the first moments where the students start to write their dissertation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-experience-3&quot;&gt;My Experience&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first chapter I wrote for my dissertation was the state of the art. I started by writing it by topics; then, it evolved for sentences with little connection with each other. Finally, in later revisions, some paragraphs were reviewed to make connections between them. Reading it after the delivery, I understood the importance of iterations in the writing, and why I couldn’t do that the first time I wrote it. Some references in the text could only be made after I knew everything that I was going to say later. If I would have been obsessed with perfection at first try, I would probably not have written so much and with so high quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-advice-3&quot;&gt;My Advice&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To write a dissertation is just like building a product - first, you have to build the Minimum Viable Product (MVP). Don’t expect to do everything right for the first time you write it. You will review your document and change it many times until it is finally ready to be delivered and presented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first goal of the writing is to explain what you did, what are your thoughts and what conclusion you can take from your work. Style is important, but it is only regarded if what you are writing is interesting. Before wasting too much time rephrasing everything you did, write what you did in a quick and dirty way. After the first version is completed, it will be much easier for you to have the big picture of your work and to rephrase paragraphs making the connection with what you will say later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it for today!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for sticking by. Click &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-have-a-thesis-part-4/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for part IV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See ya!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="thesis" /><category term="dissertation" /><category term="tips" /><summary type="html">15 tips for your thesis/dissertation - 3/4</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to have an A+ dissertation/thesis (II/IV)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/how-to-have-a-thesis-part-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to have an A+ dissertation/thesis (II/IV)" /><published>2019-08-30T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-08-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/how-to-have-a-thesis-part-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/how-to-have-a-thesis-part-2/">&lt;p&gt;Hi there!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you didn’t read the previous post, check it out &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-have-a-thesis-part-1/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I am summarizing tips I would give myself before starting the dissertation, explaining my good and bad decisions along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before, a heads up: the content of this blog post is highly subjective and related to my dissertation experience, so don’t take it as the ground truth. But do think critically about my advice and, whether you agree with them or not, comment on what you think about it&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is divided into four parts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-have-a-thesis-part-1/&quot;&gt;I - 3 tips for before starting the writing of the dissertation;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;II - 4 tips for during the writing of the dissertation;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-have-a-thesis-part-3/&quot;&gt;III - more 4 tips for during the writing of the dissertation;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-have-a-thesis-part-4/&quot;&gt;IV - 3 tips for after the writing of the dissertation.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;during-the-dissertation&quot;&gt;During the dissertation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4---when-to-research-and-write-the-state-of-the-art-of-your-work&quot;&gt;4 - When to research and write the state of the art of your work?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/img/thesis-2.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/thesis-2.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;figcaption style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;It can be important to search for articles in the beginning of the thesis&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A state of the art is a survey about the recent advances in the area you are working on. It shows the newer techniques for solving the problem you are trying to solve. In a dissertation, the state of the art chapter is usually about 10%-20% of the size of the whole document. A good state of the art shows not only the proposed techniques, but also that the writer has knowledge about the area he/she is working with. The goal is to identify the flaws in the work done previously to justify your approach to the problem. Otherwise, you will be solving a problem that is already solved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This question comes up frequently at the beginning of the dissertation work. Should you write the state of the art before you start trying to solve the problem? Or do you start writing the state of the art after having a deep knowledge about your work, and you can easily identify similar research reports?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both approaches have pros and cons. If you start to write the state of the art before start working on the dissertation, you understand better the proposed approaches to solve your problem and the recent techniques used before starting the dissertation work, and it can influence you (in a good way) to follow a certain approach. However, after the development of your work, you may have to adjust your state of the art to address the unexpected problems you may have encountered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you write the state of the art after the dissertation work is done, you will have more in-depth knowledge about your work at the time you are writing it, and your state of the art will probably be more focused on your problem. However, there is always the risk (and it is a &lt;strong&gt;BIG&lt;/strong&gt; risk!) of finding out that the problem you have solved was already solved by someone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-experience&quot;&gt;My Experience&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I initially wrote the state of the art before starting the dissertation work. It took two weeks. And it was beautiful &amp;lt;3. By the end of it, I was certain of what I was going to do next, and I knew everything about the approach to follow. When I started the dissertation work, nothing went as I expected. The data that I was told I would have was totally different from what I had thought; the approaches I thought would work did not work; even the scope of the dissertation slightly changed. As a result, by the end of it, I had to erase 60% of the state of the art previously done and start all over again; the other 40% need to be reviewed to be according to the scope of the work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-advice&quot;&gt;My Advice&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, I’m sorry. If you want to have a great state of the art, you will have to write it two times (at least…). You can start by making a state of the art before you start the dissertation work. This version will be used to explore the recent approaches to solve your problem and to start to develop your own approach to the problem. I advise you to not spend much time with syntax and grammar corrections in this version. You can even write it in bullets. After the dissertation work, you will see that this version is outdated: it contains topics that were not approached and/or is missing other topics. Do not panic! It is expected that, after the dissertation work, your understanding of the problem is different. You will have to iterate over the previous version of the state of the art and delete/write/rewrite everything until it is according to your work. After two, three or more passes on this chapter, the state of the art will be ready.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, the writing of the state of the art is a continuous loop. It must be done before and after the dissertation work, to be consistent with the entire dissertation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5---when-should-i-write-my-work&quot;&gt;5 - When should I write my work?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/img/thesis-3.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/thesis-3.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;figcaption style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;When you start writing your thesis, you start to understand better the topic you are working in.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alright, we should write the state of the art before and after the dissertation work. But when should we write the content of the dissertation work? It is important to split the dissertation work into two parts: the implementation and the writing. The implementation loosely involves the approach description and the results obtained; the writing about the implementation is another part. In which order they must be done? Obviously, you can’t write everything before the implementation is done, but do you write as you implement or do you implement everything first and then write after?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-experience-1&quot;&gt;My Experience&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have to admit that I am a &lt;em&gt;little&lt;/em&gt; anxious. Whenever I did anything of the work, I would write it down quickly so I would not forget what I had done. Looking back, I think it helped me. Allowed me to always be focused on the work to be done, and I could forget what was done previously: if I needed to go back to remember it, I would only need to read the chapter that was already previously written.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-advice-1&quot;&gt;My Advice&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Write!&lt;/strong&gt; Even if you are doing just quick tests. &lt;strong&gt;Write!&lt;/strong&gt; Even if you just need to write a description of a part of your work. &lt;strong&gt;Write!&lt;/strong&gt; The journey of the writing of a dissertation can be long, and our ability to remember everything we have done is clearly overrated. I can assure you that at the end of the dissertation you will not remember all the implementation details of the work. The only way to build a complete dissertation is to write everything as you do it. And don’t be a perfectionist: the writing does not need to be perfect, you will review it later. You only need to write to remember what you have done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;6---when-to-meet-with-my-supervisor&quot;&gt;6 - When to meet with my supervisor?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/img/thesis-4.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/thesis-4.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;figcaption style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;Meetings with your supervisor should be weekly at most.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of the most important questions. How often should you meet with your supervisor? If you meet him/her rarely, chances are that he/she will not understand the work you are doing, making it harder to receive relevant feedback. This could totally ruin your work, especially if the dissertation objective is a little blurred. In the worst possible scenario, you can end up working for nothing, since what you have done is not what your supervisor wants you to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, meetings are tiring for all intervenients. If you regularly set up long meetings to discuss details about your work, you and your supervisor will get tired quickly, and frustration will start to grow on both. Your supervisor will start to wonder if you have enough autonomy to make progress alone, without his/her input.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-experience-2&quot;&gt;My Experience&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the beginning of the work, we had a weekly meeting of about half an hour (extendable to one hour when needed) on the same day and hour of every week. At that meeting, we discussed mainly two things: what was done in the previous week and what was proposed to be done in the next. In that way, my supervisor was always following my work, and at any week we could discuss the results obtained and propose a different approach for the next week, or give me some criticism about anything I could do better before I move on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-advice-2&quot;&gt;My Advice&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I &lt;strong&gt;REALLY&lt;/strong&gt; suggest you schedule weekly meetings to talk to your supervisor about your work. Besides receiving important feedback and understand if you are on the right track, it also helps to keep up the pace week after week - if there is a week where you didn’t do anything, you will have to say it to your supervisor. Just by saying it, you will be putting (good) pressure on yourself to get the job done in the next week. It also implicitly puts pressure on your supervisor to help you when you have problems and to split the responsibilities of your work. You can often ask: should I do X or Y? Whatever the answer of your supervisor is, he/she is responsible for that choice and you do not have to answer for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all supervisors are able and willing to schedule weekly half-an-hour meetings. Maybe it’s because they think that they should only interfere in your work when you have doubts or problems; maybe it’s because they think that a monthly meeting is enough; maybe it’s because their schedule is flexible and they rather schedule meetings the week before; maybe it’s just because they are lazy (yes, it happens and it is quite common, unfortunately). Whatever it is the reason, understand it and try at all costs to schedule regular meetings. The supervisor is not at the university? You can talk to him/her with a video call. You don’t have anything to say to him? Tell him about your work in the previous week and see if he/she agrees with the approach and the results. But try to meet him/her weekly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do not schedule long meetings when they are not needed. Choose regular short meetings over monthly long meetings. Long meetings are tedious and boring - no one likes them. Besides, if you did anything wrong in the first week of the month, the work of the whole month is wasted. The key here is to have continuous and short iteration loops where your work can be evaluated, discussed and improved (have you heard of agile sprints? It follows the same principle). It improves the quality of your work and it helps you to stay focused and motivated in the task. Meetings of half-an-hour are perfect (for me). Do not make meetings of more than one hour - after the first hour, you will be much less productive. In those cases, don’t be afraid of scheduling more than one meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, but equally important, meet with your supervisor outside the meeting schedule whenever needed. During your work, there will be times when you will be stuck. You need immediate feedback to continue or you do not have a clue on what to do next in your work. In those times, do not wait for the next meeting: you can and should talk to your supervisor ASAP. There are supervisors more available than others. Independently of that, you have the right to discuss your problems with your supervisor in a short period of time. Do not be afraid of being annoying: their job is to help you when you have problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;7---how-to-prepare-your-meetings&quot;&gt;7 - How to prepare your meetings?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you go to the meetings you have to be prepared. And to be prepared not only for what you are going to say but also for the possible answers from your supervisor. You have to be aware that it must be &lt;strong&gt;YOU&lt;/strong&gt; to set up an agenda for the meeting and control it if it goes wrong. But how can you do that, if you have never learned anything about it in university?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-experience-3&quot;&gt;My Experience&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before the dissertation, I was already in a research group, with a research grant. I had the experience of being in many meetings before the dissertation and with the experience, I learned to manage meetings for them to go according to what I had planned to. Before the meeting, I made a list of everything I had to discuss. It usually started with the work of the previous week, followed by what I had in mind for the next week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During that time, I gathered a few pieces of advice that were useful for me to know at the beginning of the work. The 5 pieces of advice most important are below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-advice-3&quot;&gt;My Advice&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Make a list of everything you have to discuss in a meeting. It will be easier for you to not forget anything of what you want to discuss.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Do not wait for your supervisor to tell you what to do. Remember that you are the person that knows more about your work. You are the person that knows exactly what to do next to reach the proposed goal of your dissertation. Obviously, you can and should hear the advice from your supervisor. But you should ALWAYS propose what you should do in the next week. I can assure you that your supervisor has a different vision from yours on what’s left of your dissertation. Always be critical about what you hear and don’t be afraid to criticize your supervisor when you think he/she is wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If there is any graphical form to show the results you have, show it. Whether it is in a powerpoint, excel or code, show it. It helps the viewers to understand what you are saying and the work that you have done.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Common discussion in a meeting&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Student&lt;/strong&gt;: I have the following problem. What should I do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Student&lt;/strong&gt;: &amp;lt;Secretely wanting to use approach A&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Supervisor&lt;/strong&gt;: &amp;lt;15 minutes of discussion and searching the web about possible approaches&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Supervisor&lt;/strong&gt;: You know what? Let’s try the approaches A, B and C. At the end we will choose the best one!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Student&lt;/strong&gt;: But approaches B and C will not work…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Supervisor&lt;/strong&gt;: Well, let’s try it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Student&lt;/strong&gt;: &amp;lt;Wants to die&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever you make a question in a meeting, try to give two or three answer possibilities. If the question is about your work and you have a preference for an answer (e.g. you would like to use approach A, but the approaches B and C are also options), do not ask any question and go straight to the point: tell that you will use approach A, but B and C were also options. If your supervisor stops you and proves you wrong, follow his advice. Otherwise, just continue. In a dissertation, it is supposed for you to be autonomous. If you have a problem and you have a preferred approach to solve it, why to ask what approach should you do? If the approach is clearly wrong, your supervisor will tell you. Otherwise, you will avoid a discussion that can take a few minutes of your meeting and it will inevitably end up with you following your approach, whatever the advice of your supervisor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How it could have been:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Student&lt;/strong&gt;: For solving the problem, there are approaches A, B and C. I will use A, because it gives best results on the papers I read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Supervisor&lt;/strong&gt;: It seems OK to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Know the personalities of the people that will be in the meeting: the meeting course will be heavily influenced by them. Be careful with the chitchatters! If you let them talk too much, you will realize that the meeting will not go as planned: you will start talking about anything else but your work. Whenever that happens, you MUST re-focus the discussion in your work. Also, be careful with advice from outsiders that do not follow your work since the beginning: they can give you advice that goes in the wrong direction just because they do not understand the whole scope of your work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many more pieces of advice to prepare your meetings, but I consider these to be the five most important ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it for today!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for sticking by. Click &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-have-a-thesis-part-3/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for part III.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See ya!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="thesis" /><category term="dissertation" /><category term="tips" /><summary type="html">15 tips for your thesis/dissertation - 2/4</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to have an A+ dissertation/thesis (I/IV)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/how-to-have-a-thesis-part-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to have an A+ dissertation/thesis (I/IV)" /><published>2019-08-23T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-08-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/how-to-have-a-thesis-part-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/how-to-have-a-thesis-part-1/">&lt;p&gt;Hi there!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have recently concluded my Masters Dissertation about Control and Management Mechanisms for 5G Networks, with a 20/20 grade :) (in Portugal, the grading system goes from 1 (F) to 20 (A+) ) &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/emojis/grinning-face-facebook.png&quot; alt=&quot;grinning-face&quot; class=&quot;emojis&quot; /&gt;). While for me it was a smooth ride, for many of my colleagues it was/is really challenging to do their dissertation (or thesis, depending on the country you are studying). In this blog post, I will summarize the tips I would give myself before starting the dissertation, explaining my good and bad decisions along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, the content of this blog post is highly subjective and related to my dissertation experience, so don’t take it as the ground truth. But do think critically about my advice and, whether you agree with them or not, comment on what you think about it (I will number the tips for easy reference). Although this post is about a Masters Dissertation, it can also be (loosely) applied to a PhD work. But do note that I did not do a PhD: think critically whether this applies to you or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post will be divided into four parts: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I - 3 tips for before starting the writing of the dissertation;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-have-a-thesis-part-2/&quot;&gt;II - 4 tips for during the writing of the dissertation;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-have-a-thesis-part-3/&quot;&gt;III - more 4 tips for during the writing of the dissertation;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-have-a-thesis-part-4/&quot;&gt;IV - 3 tips for after the writing of the dissertation.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;before&quot;&gt;Before&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1---choose-the-dissertation-because-of-the-supervisor-or-because-of-the-dissertation-topic&quot;&gt;1 - Choose the dissertation because of the supervisor or because of the dissertation topic?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/img/thesis-1.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/thesis-1.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ush, this is a hot topic. Usually, some months (or weeks) before the beginning of your work, you have the chance to talk with your university Professors, to pick a topic for your dissertation. Do you start by choosing a dissertation topic and then talk to supervisors that understand that research area, or do you start by choosing a supervisor and then choose what he has to offer you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a hard question. Ideally, you would like to have both: a supervisor that you get along with and a dissertation topic that you love. That is possible more times than not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-experience&quot;&gt;My Experience&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was already in a research group before starting the dissertation, with a research grant. To choose a dissertation topic, I just went talk to my supervisor, explained to her what I had in mind, and we came to an agreement. No, it wasn’t exactly her area of research (Machine Learning/Deep Learning), but it was of both parties’ interest to make a dissertation about that. We agreed that Machine Learning techniques were going to be used to analyze and improve 5G Networks. The supervisor could give me work revision and discussion about 5G Networks, but I was on my own on how to apply the Machine Learning techniques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While during the writing of the dissertation sometimes I felt a little “lost” in what my approach should be, it has inspired me to learn online about the area, and to understand it better. Due to the freedom that I had and the confidence that I always felt by my supervisor on me, any setback in my work was quickly discussed, besides the usual weekly meetings. In the end, I felt that although another supervisor could have given me more technical insights, I had much more freedom, encouragement and logistical support that was essential to my great grade in the dissertation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-advice&quot;&gt;My Advice&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suggest going with your gut on this one. To give you an objective answer, I would say 70/30. For me, a great supervisor is more important than a great dissertation topic. A great supervisor will guarantee you 70% of your grade on your dissertation. Remember that your supervisor will be guiding you for one year (at least). You will have many meetings with him/her about the direction of your work. If you are not comfortable with him/her, or if you just don’t get along, then things can become really hard, independently of the topic of the work. What is a good supervisor? Well, that’s a topic for another post, but if you keep reading, I will give you some guidelines of what your supervisor should and shouldn’t do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being in love with a dissertation topic is important because you will spend a lot of time researching that topic. If you find a supervisor that you like and that accepts your dissertation topic, go for it! Otherwise, you will have to make a trade-off. But don’t forget: 70% of the importance to the supervisor, 30% to the dissertation topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the PhD thesis I would &lt;strong&gt;NOT&lt;/strong&gt; recommend following this approach! The PhD is a hard road for everyone, and it involves a LOT more research and background work than a Masters dissertation. You will only be able to make it to the end if you &lt;strong&gt;really&lt;/strong&gt; like the topic that you’re working in. Besides, because you will spend much more time than one year working on that topic, it is expected that you become a world expert about that. If you don’t like that topic… why you’re doing a PhD anyway?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, I would recommend to, before starting the dissertation, search for the world experts about the topic that you are in love with. Make a short-list: 2 or 3 supervisors. Then, get in touch with them to understand if they are interested and, more importantly, if they are the right supervisor for you. If you find one that you like, go for it! Otherwise, keep searching. And don’t be afraid of changing supervisors while you’re still in the first year. It is better to change in the first year than spend 3, 4 or more years regretting that decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2---understand-the-basics-before-diving-in&quot;&gt;2 - Understand the basics before diving in!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before closing the deal with a supervisor about your dissertation, you should understand the basics of the dissertation work, mainly the objective and the techniques used to solve the proposed problem. A common problem in dissertation students is that they choose a topic just by the dissertations’ name. Beware of the “hot trends” in the industry (eg. AI, 5G, Cloud, …): a cool name does not mean a cool dissertation!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-experience-1&quot;&gt;My Experience&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, let’s say I was lucky with this one… Before the dissertation deal, I really wanted to learn more about machine learning, but I didn’t know much about it. I knew the basics about it, but I knew nothing about the internals of the algorithms used, or about model tuning. In summer holidays (after accepting the dissertation deal and before starting to work on the dissertation), I learned &lt;strong&gt;a lot&lt;/strong&gt; about machine learning in three ways: free online courses, blog posts and books. Those 2 months were a crash course about machine learning algorithms and its utilization in the real world, as well as in the Deep Learning state of the art techniques. Fortunately, I loved it! At the beginning of the dissertation work, I felt a lot more confident about what to do to solve the problem, and about general knowledge about machine learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-advice-1&quot;&gt;My Advice&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before accepting the dissertation, take an hour of conversation with the supervisor. Try to understand what are the objectives of the dissertations’ work, and what are the current techniques used (or expected to be used by the supervisor). If you think that those techniques are obsolete, discuss that with the supervisor to make sure that you will not reinvent the wheel just because your supervisor finds that interesting! If you don’t understand what are the techniques that your supervisor wants you to use, take a week to learn about them (not in-depth, at least to have a grasp and understand what type of work you will be doing). If you don’t like the techniques used, feel free to reject the dissertation work (it is better to reject than to spend a year working on something you don’t like!). After accepting the dissertation, take a more in-depth look at the techniques you will be using to solve the problem, and research for the state of the art approaches. After this (sometimes boring and time-consuming) work, you will feel much more comfortable and able to do the job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3---take-a-break-after-accepting-the-dissertation&quot;&gt;3 - Take a break after accepting the dissertation!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;width:100%;height:0;padding-bottom:72%;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://giphy.com/embed/5ocAtoAPhIDcI&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; style=&quot;position:absolute&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;giphy-embed&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://giphy.com/gifs/homer-official-poster-5ocAtoAPhIDcI&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why take a break after accepting the dissertation? Shouldn’t we all start working furiously to do the work as quickly as possible? Well… &lt;strong&gt;NO!&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/emojis/pouting-face.png&quot; alt=&quot;pouting-face&quot; class=&quot;emojis&quot; /&gt; The dissertation &lt;em&gt;is not a sprint, it’s a marathon&lt;/em&gt; (more on that later). After accepting the dissertation (you usually accept it before the summer holidays), take a week to relax and think about the work you will need to do. It will require a lot of mental preparation to work a whole year in a project, especially when things go wrong. This week is not only to take in the dissertation goals and to think about them, but also to mentalize yourself that you can do it, even if things go wrong from time to time (trust me, in such a long-term work, many things &lt;strong&gt;will&lt;/strong&gt; go wrong!). It is important to mentalize yourself about the task you are facing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-experience-2&quot;&gt;My Experience&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before big steps in my life, I like to take a week to think about the step I am taking, to think about the future consequences of my decision and to understand how am I going to fulfill my goals. I did it before entering in my college course, and I did it before the starting of the dissertation work. Before the dissertation, I took a week to go to the Taizé Community: an ecumenical Christian monastic fraternity in France. I left my laptop, smartphone and electronic devices turned off to focus in nature. Besides, Taizé is known for its meditations and reflections, which allowed me to think deeply about why I was doing a dissertation, and it helped me to not give up in the hardest times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-advice-2&quot;&gt;My Advice&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No, you don’t &lt;em&gt;necessarily&lt;/em&gt; need to go to Taizé to take a break. But I would recommend going away from distractions, from electronic devices and from your routine. A week camping in the forest is also a good option. If you can’t be unavailable for a week, at least do it for a weekend. If you can’t or don’t like camping, you can go to a bungalow and take walks in the forest, for example. The key here is to go away from your routine. Only when you disconnect from the world you can really think deeply about what you want and how to reach it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it for today!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for sticking by. Click &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-have-a-thesis-part-2/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for part II.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See ya!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="thesis" /><category term="dissertation" /><category term="tips" /><summary type="html">15 tips for your thesis/dissertation - 1/4</summary></entry></feed>
